MARIANA CHAVES

Statistician and data scientist

@ marianach16@gmail.com
https://m-chaves.github.io/

J +33 674280830 or +506 64628057

Union Series 2016 Union Series 2017 Union

ABOUT ME

I'm a **statistician and data scientist** with 7 years of working experience in data modeling, visualization, extraction, and transformation. Recently, I have been researching explainable and interpretable AI. In particular, prototype-based interpretable neural networks and local interpretable model-agnostic explanations (LIME). More broadly, I have been working with natural language processing and text classification models.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Research internship

13S and Inria, France

2022

Research on prototype-based interpretable neural networks approaches for text classification. This study lied on the framework of ANR TRACTIVE, a project that regroups researchers several disciplines for the understanding of gender representation in visual media. It involved implementing various NLP techniques and text classification models.

Research internship

Inria and Laboratoire J.A. Dieudonné of the Université Côte d'Azur, France

2021

Research on model agnostic interpretability methods in the ambit of images. More specifically, improving resampling process for local interpretable model-agnostic explanations (LIME).

Junior data scientist

Walmart Supply Chain Analytics USA

2018 - 2020

Directed and developed data analysis projects to provide agile solutions to business partners. Main projects included an anomaly detection system, statistical sampling design, and consumption layer design.

Data analyst

Walmart Supply Chain Analytics USA

2017 - 2018

Worked in data extraction, transformation, and visualization. Main projects included statistical process control techniques and KPI development.

Data analyst

BAC Credomatic Regional Compliance Management, Costa Rica

2016

Developed money laundering detection models for five Central American countries.

EDUCATION

MSc DATA SCIENCE AND ARTIFI-CIAL INTELLIGENCE

Université Côte d'Azur (UCA), France

2020 - 2022

Honors Graduate (Mention Très Bien)

BACHELOR IN STATISTICS

University of Costa Rica (UCR), Costa Rica

2013 - 2017

Honors Graduate

AWARDS

Highest GPA among Statistics majors for three consecutive years: 2013, 2014, 2015.

University of Costa Rica (UCR)

Honorable Mention: Ninth highest score on Admission Exam 2012.

University of Costa Rica (UCR)

Honorable Mention: Highest score on Admission Exam 2012.

Technological Institute of Costa Rica (TEC)

SQL

MAIN SKILLS

Python R LaTeX

LANGUAGES

Spanish - C2 (Native) English - C1

French - B2

